A Guide to the John Brown's Raid Commissary Accounts of the Adjutant General, 1859
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
John Brown's Raid Commissary Accounts of the Adjutant General, 1859
Library of Virginia
39025
.23 cubic feet
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
No acquisition information available.
Biographical/Historical Information
On the night of 16 October 1859, John Brown led a group of radical abolitionists against the U.S. Arsenal at Harpers Ferry in Jefferson County, Virginia, with the purpose of arming and inciting a slave rebellion. Brown and many of his conspirators were captured and some killed when U.S. Marines under Col. Robert E. Lee surrounded and stormed the engine house where Brown's men had been trapped. John Brown and his men were taken to Charlestown where they were tried and later hanged on 2 December 1859. In order to guard against threats of invasion, Governor Wise called up a number of militia units to protect Charlestown before and after the execution. General William Booth Taliaferro commanded the 4th Division Virginia Militia stationed in Charlestown, Virginia. Taliaferro named Maj. George W.T. Kearlsey Acting Commissary of Subsistence by General Order No. 3 on November 24, 1859.
Scope and Content Information
This series contains board accounts, provision returns, receipts, and requisitions submitted by militia units to Maj. George W.T. Kearsley, Acting Commissary of Subsistence. The board accounts document expenses incurred by the militia stationed at Charlestown and Harper's Ferry in November and December 1859. This file also includes consolidated accounts, a list of debts due the state to individuals who boarded soldiers, and a list of accounts due the commissary from persons who boarded soldiers but who refuse to put in any claims. The provision returns were completed by company commanders and enumerate the number of men in the unit, the number of days, and the amount of specific rations (e.g. beef, pork, flour) consumed during that time period. There is a separate file for provision returns issued prior to December 8, 1859. The remaining provision returns are arranged alphabetically by unit name and include receipts. Lastly, there are requisitions by unit commanders including vouchers and receipts for provisions.
Contents List
- John Brown's Raid Commissary accounts, 1859
  - Board Accounts, 1859 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Provision Returns - Issued Before December 8, 1859 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Provision Returns and Receipts - Black Horse Company, 1859 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Provision Returns and Receipts - Clark Guards, 1859 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Provision Returns and Receipts - Fincastle Riflemen, 1859 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Provision Returns and Receipts - Loudoun Light Horse, 1859 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Provision Returns and Receipts - Mountain Guards, 1859 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Provision Returns and Receipts - Petersburg City Guard, 1859 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Provision Returns and Receipts - Petersburg Grays, 1859 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Provision Returns and Receipts - Portsmouth National Grays, 1859 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Provision Returns and Receipts - Richardson Guards, 1859 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Provision Returns and Receipts - Tenth Legion, 1859 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Provision Returns and Receipts - Washington Guards, 1859 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Provision Returns and Receipts - West Augusta Guard, 1859 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Provision Returns and Receipts - Woodis Riflemen, 1859 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Provision Returns and Receipts - Wythe Grays, 1859 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Requisitions, 1859 (Box 1, Folder 17)